<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cardan his Three books of consolation English'd ...</title>
            <title>De consolatione. English</title>
            <author>Cardano, Girolamo, 1501-1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12278177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12278177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58560</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33618)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58560)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 132:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cardan his Three books of consolation English'd ...</title>
                  <title>De consolatione. English</title>
                  <author>Cardano, Girolamo, 1501-1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], ii, 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Aylmer ... and S. Croutch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: De consolatione.</note>
                  <note>A different translation from that of Thomas Bedingfield published in the 16th century.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58560:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58560:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CARDAN HIS <hi>THREE BOOKS</hi> OF CONSOLATION Engliſh'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe in theſe Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons,</hi> and <hi>S. Croutch,</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms,</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58560:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58560:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have here an Antidote againſt every Trouble, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by that Phyſitian, whoſe prodigious Parts, and ſingular Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, have made him Admir'd and Envy'd by moſt of the Learned World. He had ('tis true) his <hi>Deliriums</hi> in common with all great Wits; but his lucid intervals were ſuch, as made him paſs in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of ſome, that read his Works, for <hi>more than a Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:58560:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:58560:3"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58560:4"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap> not the fate of thoſe other Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Monuments, which periſhed in the <hi>Barbarian</hi> Wars. For as he ſhewed himſelf a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Philoſopher in all his Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſo 'tis not to be imagined, but that on this occaſion, he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did whatever he had done before: ſeeing the Subject he Handled was neither Common, Foreign, nor Feigned; but ſprang from his own Natural Affection, and great trouble of mind.</p>
               <p n="2">II, Now although we want this uſeful Book, to furniſh us with thoſe excellent Arguments, which (without doubt) he made uſe of to quiet his own mind. Yet ſhall not this diſcourage us (conſidering our need) from of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the beſt we can deviſe:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58560:4"/>as thoſe who cannot get ſtately Pallaces to dwell in, muſt be contented with ſimple Cottages.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And the neceſſity of ſuch Diſcourſes as theſe appears hence; That ſuppoſing our ſelves free from all other vexations, yet will the remembrance and dread of Death, four all our preſent enjoyments.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But beſides the fear of death, how many other troubles are there againſt which we had need be fortified? Our Hunger is ſatisfied with Meat, our Thirſt with Drink, our Wearineſs with Reſt: But the fear of evils (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther real or imaginary) is ſo rooted and fruitful in our minds, that unleſs it be obviated by wiſe conſiderations, tis impoſſible to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58560:5"/>keep them ſerene, and undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; ſeeing it leads us from one diſcontented thought to another without end.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I know not what benefit others may reap by this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as to my ſelf, (for whom I chiefly deſigned this Book) the conſiderations contained therein, have abundantly profited me. And as t'was ſaid of <hi>Aſclepiodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> that he could paint without colours; ſo ſhall I without any Art or Skill declare, how greatly we err both in our Opinions and Wills.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Now although the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our cares and miſeries be great, yet if nearly conſidered, we ſhall find ſeveral of them to be ſuch as need no Medicine; as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58560:5"/>thoſe which men voluntarily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo: For who will attempt to comfort <hi>Marcus Regulus</hi> in his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; whom neither Natural Affection to his Children, and Relations, nor the intreaties of his Friends, could perſuade from haſtening out of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented at <hi>Carthage.</hi> Such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Spirits were the Holy Martyrs, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. But there are other kind of hardſhips, which the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate do not refuſe, for the ſake of Honour, Pleaſure, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: Some ſerve Kings, others their Miſtreſſes; one man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes his time and himſelf with Study; another commits himſelf to the mercyleſs Sea, and are ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58560:6"/>little troubled at theſe toyls, that it grieves them to be withheld from engaging in them. Some led on only by hope, ſpend their days in ſolitary places; refuſing all the comforts and convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of this life; Macerating themſelves with Faſtings, and Watchings, who being asked for what end they do this, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, for hope, that after death, they ſhall receive an everlaſting recompence. Some take great pains meerly for Pleaſure, as <hi>Harveſt Labourers, who after long Toyl and Sweat in Summers Sun, do notwithſtanding Dance when the Pipe or Viol Sounds.</hi> Others ſit at play till their Feet ake with Cold; the pleaſure of the ſport exceeding the ſharpneſs of the pain.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58560:6"/>
               <p>To begin with private Evils, we may take this for a certain truth, that it matters not to happy living, what a mans For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune be; ſeeing there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of life, but admits the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of ſome vertue; and <hi>what wiſe man will torment himſelf in adverſity; conſidering how vain, ſhort and uncertain the Life of Man is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. In what a kind of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty do we live, when a man riſes from his Bed in the Morning, to be uncertain of his return to Reſt again: or when he lies down to ſleep, whether ever he ſhall riſe. Well do the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in their Language call man a ſhadow, for in truth he is no more, his body being ſo frail
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58560:7"/>and brittle, and expoſed to ſo many dangers, that nothing is more to be admired, than that it ſhould uſually ſubſiſt ſo long.</p>
               <p>I allow thoſe Philoſophers to be in the right, who made all things conſiſt in Opinion. For what Cuſtom, Law, or Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has ſo far prevailed, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to meet with contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>The Philoſophers had never contended ſo long among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, had the matter of their debates been evident and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. For what man is ſo mad as to affirm the Swan to be Black, or the Crow white, ſeeing the matter here is to be decided by common ſenſe.</p>
               <p>But touching what is Good and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58560:7"/>Evil (Good Lord) what Diſputes have aroſe, what wranglings and oppoſitions? Which makes me remember a pleaſant ſtory writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by an Ancient Poet, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well ſets forth our Folly.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. When mighty <hi>Jupiter</hi> had made the Heavens, the Earth, the Sea, Men, and Beaſts, he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly conſidered, that unleſs he alloted Puniſhments and Rewards for mens Deſerts, they would be not only guilty of great irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities towards one another, but Affront the Gods themſelves; for which cauſe he commanded <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> to make two brazen Tuns, the one to receive all that was good, the other whatſoever was evil, making both good and evil things wing'd, that Mortals might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58560:8"/>more conveniently receive them according to their Deſerts. But the Goddeſs <hi>Pandora</hi> a buſie huſwife, mov'd with that reſtleſs curioſity which is common to all the Sex, muſt needs be peeping in 'em, when immediately both the good and evil flew their ways, the good up to Heaven, the Evil down to Hell, hope only remaining in the Veſſel of evils, and ſuſpicion in the other. Which news when <hi>Jupiter</hi> heard, he takes the empty Barrels and in a mad raging fit, throws 'em down; which being perceiv'd by mortal men, who are deſirous (as you know) of News, they immediately draw near, and embrace the empty Veſſels; perſuading themſelves they had gotten both good and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58560:8"/>evil; whereas in truth neither good nor evil happen'd to either of them; only they that light on the better Veſſel, found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves poſſeſt with an opinion of good mixt with ſuſpicion; and the other with opinion of evil mixt with hope.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Like to what Travellers tell us touching ſuch as paſs over the Deſarts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> who chancing to tread upon ſome piece of Iron, or other cold thing, are ſuddenly ſtartled with fear, leaſt they have trodden on ſome venemous Serpent; ſo does the bare opinion of good and evil perplex all mortal Creatures: altho' 'tis certain all good things are flown up into Heaven, and all evil down into Hell. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58560:9"/>therefore ever ſince the great <hi>Jupiter</hi> has taken no notice of mens deſerts.</p>
               <p>Now altho' this be but a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet does it give as ſatisfactory an account, as the definitions of Philoſophers or School-men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Afflictions advantagious. Grief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. The miſchiefs of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs and ſelf-love.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS all earthly joys are vain and unſtable, ſo in the World to come all things are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, aſſured and everlaſting, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Almighty God calls us by the ſufferance of theſe Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58560:9"/>which we term Evils, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Prophet, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou wert beloved of God it was expedient that Temptation ſhould try thee.</hi> For Almighty God not unlike a Father that entirely loves his Children, brings them up in all continency and ſobriety, reſtraining them from pleaſures and not ſuffering 'em without chaſtiſement, to live wickedly. And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſuch as he lightly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he ſuffers to wallow without controul, into all manner of luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and riot. Shall we ſay the life of ſuch Servants is more happy than that of thoſe Sons. For as Gold is purified in the furnace, ſo is the life of a good man pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by adverſity. But what ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58560:10"/>all the ſufferings of this World (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays) if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the glory which ſhall be revealed. Will not he that believes this rejoyce in adverſity and lament in proſperity? and amidſt his miſeries perſuade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that God makes trial of his faith, that he may afterwards take him to himſelf. If in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting worldly glory we uſually ſo greatly rejoyce, altho we know it to be of ſhort continuance, what ought we not to do for this Heavenly glory, which is everlaſting, certain, and fully ſatisfactory. Did men believe theſe things, they would ſave me the labour of writing, for who ſo mad as not to be willing to change this ſhort life, for that which is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58560:10"/>Everlaſting, this frail for that firm, this unhappy for that moſt happy, this troubleſom for that moſt quiet.</p>
               <p>'Tis our infidelity that makes us miſerable: For what can be more profitable after death, or more comfortable in this life, than the hope of that which is to come. And tho' the ſame were not, yet ought not a man to be dejected, ſeeing there's ſcarcely any miſery ſo great but is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſome advantage. And as adverſity and misfortunes have been to ſome men a means of their promotion, ſo has Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity been to others an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their miſery. The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude of <hi>Ventidius</hi> occaſion'd his becoming Conſul.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58560:11"/>
               <p>What's more irkſom than Sickneſs; Yet did it profit the Emperor <hi>Auguſtus</hi> being in Arms againſt <hi>Brutus.</hi> For being warn'd by his Phyſician to remove from his Tent, he by Sleep recover'd his health, which had he done for any other reſpect, 'twould have been diſhonorable: And had he not done it, he had certainly bin ſlain or forced to fly. <hi>Ploti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a Philoſopher of <hi>Plato</hi>'s ſect, had among others a Scholar na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Ornucius Marcellus</hi> greatly diſeaſed with the Gout and Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey; who thro' diligent hearing of his Maſter (who diſputed and read with great ſweetneſs and facility,) forgot oft times to eat: and ſo with attentive hearing became a ſingular Philoſopher,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58560:11"/>and with much abſtinence reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd his health. A Diſtemper'd Body do's oft-times much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the health of the mind.</p>
               <p n="2">II. It is obſerv'd that Sickly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the moſt part live longer than thoſe of a firmer conſtitution.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 3d. tho' he was a learn'd Man and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to attain to the Papacy, yet did the opinion of his Old age and ſickly body, chiefly occaſion his advancement. Amongſt other advantages which Adverſity has, this is not the leaſt, that, <hi>a Man's misfortunate day's once paſt, he liveth the reſt of his life with greater delight.</hi> Who can reliſh health, that has never been ſick? Who knows the ſweetneſs of his Country, ſo well as he that has
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58560:12"/>been long abroad? Or <hi>who can take pleaſure in Riches but he that has been poor?</hi> As Salt ſavours Meat, ſo do's paſt miſery ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our lives more pleaſant. What turn'd more to <hi>Tully</hi>'s advantage than his Baniſhment, when his Goods were ſold, and his Houſe pull'd down, then he found how welcom he was to the Citizens, how uſeful to his Country, and how dear to his Friends: and had he modeſtly uſed his Glory, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hapned to him in his life could have been more to his advantage. Howſoever, In all misfortunes of a Man's life this argument is of great importance, that <hi>we muſt of neceſſity comfort our ſelves at laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58560:12"/>III. Neither do's ſorrow ſerve for any other end, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe care, and render our minds more unapt for good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. Continual grief and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will drive us at length upon deſperation. <hi>Since then 'tis in our own power to aggravate or diminiſh our cares,</hi> 'tis the part of a wiſe man to disburden him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of ſorrow and patiently bear whatſoever happens.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. An undaunted ſuffering of Adverſity has oft helped gallant ſpirits. For we generally ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt take pity of thoſe that coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly undergo any misfortune, and preſume more of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and vertue, than of thoſe that in like extremity give way to fear. <hi>Agis</hi> the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monian</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58560:13"/>King, being condemned to dye, was drawn with a Cord to the place of execution; it hapned he ſpyed a Servant of his ſtanding by weeping, to whom he ſaies; my Friend, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee forbear weeping, for being unjuſtly condemn'd, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more worthy of life, than thoſe that put me to death. And having thus ſaid, he willingly ſtrangled himſelf. When <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vola</hi> determin'd to kill the King <hi>Porſenna,</hi> he for his valiant and voluntary confeſſion receiv'd par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; which if he had not done, but with denial craved Mercy, beſides diſhonor, he would have ſuffered a moſt cruel death. In ſhort, patience in Captivity, and magnanimity in Adverſity have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58560:13"/>ever been prais'd and found to be moſt advantageous.</p>
               <p n="5">V. It is a guilty Conſcience that makes a man unhappy. A man is nothing but his mind, if that be out of order, all's amiſs, and if that be well, all the reſt is at eaſe.</p>
               <p>I remember a certain Rich man, falling mad, ſnatched up a Straw and complain'd he ſhould dye for hunger, becauſe there was no Corn within the empty Ears. <hi>Would we know why we are Fools, 'tis becauſe we count our ſelves wiſe. Socrates</hi> who by <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Oracle was ſaid to be the wiſeſt of all Mortals, confeſſed he knew but one thing, and that was he knew nothing. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> that famous Aſtronomer, was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58560:14"/>wont to ſay that man who pleaſed himſelf was hateful to the gods. And he pleaſeth himſelf that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines himſelf wiſe or provident, and imputeth all to his own wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and conduct.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Men pull down Evils on themſelves. Pleaſure ever attended with pain. No condition of life free from trouble. Kings more miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than other men.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. SOme men there be who may be compared to the <hi>Gudgin,</hi> that knows under the Bait lies a Hook, yet hurry'd and driven
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58560:14"/>on by luſt, run themſelves into infinite miſery. 'Tis ſaid of that Fiſh that ſhe firſt craftily (and yet fooliſhly enough) with her Tail beats the Bait from the Hook, but if that will not do, bites it. Whereas we more ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs run on without either fear or wit.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Perhaps thou wilt ſay I would have Pleaſure without Pain: 'Tis contrary to nature, for Joy is continually attended by Sorrow, Glory with Envy; Wiſedom is not gotten without labour, Wealth is not obtain'd without care, Children are kept with trouble, Banquetting is attended by Sickneſs, Eaſe with poverty, Power with envy, Quiet with wearineſs. <hi>Every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58560:15"/>man has ſomething to complain of.</hi> Some be afflicted with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, others want Children, this man is Sick, that man wants a Wife, and this man would be rid of his. But that which is moſt ſtrange is, that to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and liable to no misfortune, is alſo a calamity. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Polycrates</hi> that having never met with any calamity, he greatly deſired to experience ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap, and therefore threw into the Sea a Ring of great value, on purpoſe to have cauſe to complain. But Fortune it ſeems having ſworn his happineſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored it again in a Fiſh.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But leaſt I be thought to argue with Fables. Pray what pleaſure do Princes receive at
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58560:15"/>their Meals, when continual eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Delicacies, has taken away their Taſte. <hi>'Tis Coarſe and Homely Fare that makes Finer Meats Relliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or how can he be happy that never felt Grief. This is certain, that without Adverſity a man cannot Live comfortably, nor take delight in Mirth without ſome Sorrow. And <hi>is it not a comfort in our Calamity to have not only one Man for a Companion, but all Mankind.</hi> What's more ſeemly than a Common-wealth well Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd: yet what's more hard than to Live in it. The <hi>Romans</hi> by their Severity to themſelves Conquer'd the whole World. But what is more Slaviſh than living under ſuch Laws, when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58560:16"/>Men are conſtrained to Marry, Labour with their own Hands, Educate Children, and follow the Wars: The bringing up of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (eſpecially many) to a poor man, ſeems to ſurpaſs all Sorrows. What is more Dangerous and Laborious than War, wherein Men toyl Night and Day, ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Winters Snow, and march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Summers Sun, Watching continually, climbing Mountains, and ſayling the Seas, afflicted with hunger and thirſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to thoſe Extremities as to kill or be killed. So that it is no wonder to ſee how willingly Soldiers behold the diſplayed En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and receive the News of Battel, ſeeing they ſhall by a happy Victory be either eaſed of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58560:16"/>their travail, or by death termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a painful Life. The <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> lived ſo hardly at home, that it never grieved them to ſerve abroad in the Wars.</p>
               <p>Neither be Kings (whom Men reſpect as Happy) exempt from Common Calamities, but rather more Unfortunate than other Men. Tis obſervable that Poets <hi>have ever laid the Scenes of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies in Kings Pallaces, and on the contrary, Comedies and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Entertainments in private Houſes.</hi> Princes Pallaces are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually inhabited by ſuch foul Monſters as Envy, Hatred, Luſt, and Oppreſſion. Even the Princes mind is the ſeat of all theſe, whereby he is never ſuffered to ſleep quietly by Night, nor
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58560:17"/>reſt by day. Sometimes the thoughts of his groſs Enormities terrifie his mind, otherwhiles his quiet is diſturbed with Jealouſies and Suſpicions, ſtudying Day and Night to weaken the force of Neighbouring Princes, and keep himſelf ſecure from his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Encroachments. <hi>Suppoſing, in ſhort, a Prince never ſo Juſt and Prudent, yet is it almoſt impoſſible for him to be void of Cares and Fears.</hi> Seeing then all mortal men be ſubject to ſome kind of vexation, who art thou that ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to live free from that Law to which all others are ſubject? <hi>Why doſt thou not complain, that thou art not made immortal, winged, and King of the whole world, and free from all misfortunes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58560:17"/>VI. Tis ſtoryed of the Hares that conſidering how they were perſecuted they became deſperate, and reſolved to drown themſelves in the next River; for which cauſe being one morning aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, on they went to effect their determination; The Frogs that happened to be upon the bank hearing a noiſe, for fear leapt into the water: which when the Hares heard, and finding it was for fear of them, they changed their minds: becauſe the Frogs more unhappy than they, yet ſought to preſerve their Lives. Truly the Adverſity of others, never made my Misfortunes ſeem the leſs: But the unavoidableneſs of Troubles, to which all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are ſubject, has much miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58560:18"/>my private Griefs. For who but a mad man will lament that which cannot be helped. A wiſe man conſidering the courſe of ſublunary things, will expect any kind of miſhap, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt the worſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Time a certain Remedy of all Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Death makes all equal.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. 'TIS alſo to be remembred, that Time is a medicine for all manner of Troubles. <hi>Who grieves for his Grandmother, that dyed fourſcore years ago?</hi> or Goods loſt thirty years ſince. Such is the nature of time, that firſt it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58560:18"/>leſſens our extream ſorrow or joy, ſecondly, wears out our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and laſtly, works in us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſs of what is paſt. <hi>Why cannot we then have that influence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver our ſelves, by which we may effect a ſpeedy cure.</hi> A great argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is of wiſdom to bear that with patience immediately, which others cannot do till a great deal of time be paſt. Set we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us the Examples of ſeveral worthy men, that have patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undergone the utmoſt of Fortunes Malice. Be modeſt in proſperity as well as in Adverſity. And pluck up a good heart, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading our ſelves that our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy days be paſt, and better times will ſucceed. Make not thy Life a burden to thee, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58560:19"/>thou art that has light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Valley of Tears. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>the Life of man compared with Eternity is leſs than nothing.</hi> That the whole World will paſs away and thou with it, and never after return again: ſo that it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not what thy preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may be.</p>
               <p n="2">II. What will it avail thee 300 years hence, whether thou haſt been an Emperour, or a Cobler: Whether thou haſt been <hi>Lucullus</hi> or <hi>Iris, Xenophon</hi> or <hi>Cleon,</hi> a Slave or a Free-man, happy or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy. Whether thou haſt dyed in thy Bed or at the Gallows. How does this our time paſs away, how ſpeedily, how forcibly? what a good fancy was that of him that cut in one Stone three Faces,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58560:19"/>a Childs, a young mans and an old mans, admitting as it were no difference. <hi>Imagine that now which will really happen; the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of time, and thou ſhalt find all things, nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ought to behave our ſelves like men in Priſon that are in hopes of deliverance, who altho attended with wearineſs at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, yet (eſpecially if men of courage) yield not themſelves up to Grief.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Seeing then we all expect equality in death, the rich may be ſorrowful but not the poor. Were it now proclaimed as 'twas in the times of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> that all Goods ſhould be Equally divided, which would be moſt troubled? Foraſmuch then as thoſe that be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58560:20"/>rich muſt one day be poor, and they that be poor one day rich, be thou contented.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Our folly hinders us from ſetting a due eſtimate on things: It makes Pygmies become Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, hides our happineſs from us, and makes us afraid of our own ſhadows. If there be any thing to be <hi>fear'd or deſir'd in this life 'tis moral Good or evil, a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or a quiet Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:58560:20"/>
            <head>CARDAN OF <hi>CONSOLATION.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">BOOK II.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The folly of our unwillingneſs to dye. And vanity of ſuch as are ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about their Funerals. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of Old Age.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. HItherto we have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd of Human Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and their remedies in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58560:21"/>Come we now to Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. And firſt of the fear of death. Conſider, what happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thou haſt found in life, to make thee ſo much in love with it. Doſt thou alone poſſeſs any delight which we have not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd. We have ſeen the Stars, the Heavens, Mountains, Seas, Rivers, Lakes, Fields, Gardens, Cities and pleaſant Villages, had Muſick, Songs, Banquets, Love intrigues and Dalliances, with all ſorts of earthly delights, nor have we wanted Learning to judg, diſpute, make Verſes and Orations; born Offices, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted our ſelves honorably of them, ſatisfied the neceſſities of our Children, Friends and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and lived together with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58560:21"/>them in good reputation; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting neither Food nor Rayment, and abounded in all the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of this life: and yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but unfeignedly ſay with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon. Vanity of vanity, and all is vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. As to other mens experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; let them ſpeak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to my own part, I have felt more Grief than Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this World. Seeing then this love of life availeth nothing, nay tho it were deſirable, tis better to caſt off this burthen of Cares and <hi>like an honeſt man reſtore that which thou haſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed.</hi> Whereas if thou tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thy ſelf, what doſt thou get thereby, but to conſume in dying that ſmall time which is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58560:22"/>remaining; ſeeing whatſoever time is ſpent in thinking of death, may juſtly be ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. I am much taken with the ſaying of <hi>Agathius,</hi> who tells us that Death does not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſickneſs, and all other vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations; but whereas theſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen often, that comes but once. <hi>Neither can Death be accounted a great Evil, ſeeing it comes upon ſo light occaſions, and is ſo ready at hand.</hi> Such things as are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to our natures are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ſoon found, whereas there's nothing <hi>more common or ſooner found than death.</hi> Death is to be met with every where, and in all things, in Fire and Water, Air, Wind, Thunder, Earth-quakes, wild Beaſts, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58560:22"/>and Fowls, in Meat and Drink, Bed, Trees, Sleep, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Joy, Laughter, Company, Diſcord, Concord, and finally, in all Circumſtances. <hi>Philome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> ſeeing his Aſs eat Raiſins, bid his Boy give him ſome Wine to drink, and fell into ſuch a fit of laughter, that he kill'd himſelf. <hi>Coma</hi> being apprehended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined for Robbery by <hi>Rutilus</hi> the Conſul, required time to make his defence, and putting down his Head between his Knees, he ſtopped his own breath, and died ſo quietly that his Guard knew nothing of it till they ſaw him dead.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Seeing then men die with ſuch eaſe, what can Death be better compared to than a Dream.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58560:23"/>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> dyed with a Jeſt in his month. Do we think then that he felt any great grief? Certainly no; for men cannot jeſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme pain, the mind being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with far greater matters. This is <hi>alſo be to admir'd, that men ſhould with the greateſt averſation dread</hi> Death, and <hi>yet earneſtly uſe thoſe means that bring it.</hi> The luſtful perſon, preferreth his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure before it, the injur'd his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, the Eater his gluttony, the Ambitious his honor, the Covetous his riches, the Soldier his ſpoyl, the Mother her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the Merchant his traffick, and the Student his learning. <hi>They are to be eſteemed moſt valiant, that ſcorn to dye unleſs a weighty cauſe requires it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58560:23"/>IV. Some perhaps be of <hi>Aepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnus</hi> his mind, <hi>Dye ſays he I would not, but to be dead I care not:</hi> Pray what hurt is it to want, hunger, thirſt, grief, labour, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, fear, and in ſhort all thoſe Evils in general which the Soul muſt of neceſſity want being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Body; and ſeeing it dies not, but in lieu of theſe troubles partakes of heavenly joys: why ſhould we not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept of this change. It was the ſaying of <hi>Socrates</hi> that Death may be fitly compared to a ſound ſleep.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I remember my Father <hi>Faucius Cardan</hi> was wont to ſay he continually deſired death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when he ſlept he taſted the pleaſures of it; meaning, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58560:24"/>that all ſenſual delights contain more pain than pleaſure, and therefore it was better being without 'em. <hi>Diogenes</hi> being ſick, and found by his Phyſician aſleep, was asked how he did, well, anſwered he, for one Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther envyeth another. <hi>Coſmas Medices</hi> (a wiſe and vertuous man in our times) being at the point of death, cloſed his own eyes, which his Wife ſeeing, demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reaſon; I do it ſays he, <hi>becauſe it is cuſtomary. Socrates</hi> being by <hi>Crito</hi> perſuaded to eſcape out of Priſon, as well for his Friends ſake as his own, refuſed to do it, anſwering wiſely; I am going into thoſe parts, where I ſhall certainly find as good, or perhaps better friends that thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58560:24"/>I leave behind. And you will alſo bear me company in a ſhort ſpace. In fine, Death doth certainly take away more Evils than it bringeth. If Death be an Evil, to be dead is to eſcape it, but if it be a Good, thou haſt no cauſe to lament. That it is one of theſe no man doubts.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. I remember that being much afflicted with a Tertian Ague, the ſeventh Fit of it laid me for dead. In which time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' every Member was almoſt deprived of its uſe, yet felt I nothing worſe than a certain kind of tickling throughout my whole body accompanied with no ſmall pleaſure. Poſſeſſed I was indeed with fear I ſhould dye. Which made me enquire of others who
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58560:25"/>had been at the point of death, whether they felt any great ſmart or not, who told me that in the Head or Tooth-ach, or ſuch like diſtemper they endured grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pain. I have obſerved that altho' Women and Children be moſt fearful to take Medicines, and yield to cutting of Veins, yet when at the point of death, they neither complain nor lament, but are rather offended if we ſeek to preſerve their lives.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. What is our life, but a continual toyl, perpetually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Labour, Suſpicions, and Dangers. <hi>What delight is there that is not followed by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi> Thou art revenged, then look to thy ſelf; Haſt thou eaten thy fill, then Satiety will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58560:25"/>offend thee? Haſt thou lightly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ined, then thy appetite is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atisfied. Doſt thou give way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Luſt, expect ſadneſs and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he end ſickneſs. In ſhort, either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy deſire is not ſatisfied, and art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hereby ſtill diſcontented or elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormented with Satiety, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entance.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Obſerve how bruit Beaſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ield to death, how little they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re tormented with the thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f it before-hand, and how pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iently they endure it when it comes: and <hi>can we ſuppoſe God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as endow'd them with greater gifts of fortitude than our ſevles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good Man is always ready to lay down his life. <hi>Callicratides</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Captain, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Soothſayer foretel Victory
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58560:26"/>to the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> and death to himſelf, anſwered: <hi>Sparta</hi> in loſing me will not be at all weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. What great acts have been performed by ſuch who fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not death, how happy have been their Lives, how glorious their ends. In fine, why ſhall we refuſe to yield to that equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which makes the Beggar a Prince, and the Tyrant ſimple, and harmleſs duſt.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Neither the vaſt Army of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> nor Treaſure of <hi>Tybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> or Cruelty of <hi>Antonius,</hi> could any whit prevail againſt Death. We ſhall all be equal and harmleſs there: and except Vertue, there will be no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>No man can be ignorant of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58560:26"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his journey.</hi> 'Tis a fond and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y opinion that renders this ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yful and advantagious a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er unpleaſant and terrible. Upon what light cauſes have ſome ſlain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemſelves. I knew a Scholar a Countrey-man of ours in <hi>Padoa,</hi> who being ſlighted by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman with whom he was in Love, Poyſon'd himſelf. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her in our City for vexation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the price of Corn fell, Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed himſelf. Another, and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ikewiſe an <hi>Italian,</hi> finding he could not conveniently pay his Debts, Drowned himſelf: I ſaw a Woman who for mere ſorrow that ſhe had committed Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tery (asking God forgiveneſs for what ſhe had done) immediately drank Poyſon. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> altho'
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58560:27"/>ſhe might have liv'd in honor, yet to prevent her being carried about in Tryumph, caus'd a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to ſting her to death. <hi>Porcia</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Cato</hi> and Wife to <hi>Brutus,</hi> (a moſt heroick ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Woman) hearing her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was ſlain, eat burning Coals and died. <hi>Damocles</hi> a beautiful Boy beloved by King <hi>Demetrius,</hi> being watch'd when he ſhould enter naked into the Bath, and knowing the King deſign'd to abuſe his body, div'd down to the bottom of the Water and drowned himſelf. 'Tis endleſs to relate Inſtances of thoſe that for Fear, Love, Grief, Anger, and other occaſions of no weight have ſought their own deaths. We read moreover of whole
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58560:27"/>Legions, that offered themſelves to apparent deſtruction. As they that were with <hi>Leonida</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Expedition. <hi>What would not theſe People have ventured on a great occaſion, when for ſo ſmall a matter they did not refuſe to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">XI. But perhaps thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I do not fear Death, for not being an Evil, 'tis neceſſary; and to fear that which cannot be avoided, were vain, cowardly, and hurtful. Yet would I dye eaſily and ſuch a death as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> deſir'd and obtained; for by living till I am Old, I ſhall not only gain a longer life, but alſo an eaſier death.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. 'Twas <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s opinion that Old men dyed not only without pain, but alſo without
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58560:28"/>any ſeeling of death, becauſe the heat of their bodies was quenched. Which may be illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by this Example; If you go about to draw a Tooth, that is not looſe, you feel great ſmart, but if 'twere looſe of it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; its drawn without any trouble. So green Youth with extreme reluctancy yields to death, whereas old Folks in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing feel almoſt no grief at all. In <hi>India</hi> men are ſaid to live commonly an hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, by reaſon of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Air and the Peoples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without cares. Whereas we continuing in cares, luxury, and immoderate labours, choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Air for profit, not for health, bring upon our ſelves diſeaſes and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58560:28"/>untimely death, and yet lay the fault on Nature. How much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were it to know how to uſe the benefit of Nature, if thou eſteemeſt Life to be ſuch a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and deſirable thing. How have Hermites lived ſo long but by living temperately and void of care? <hi>The longeſt life is ſhort, becauſe death will certainly put an end to it: Only Vertue and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy actions can extend it, and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Vice ſhorten it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Alexander,</hi> tho' he lived not above 33 years, died an Old man, by means of his great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits. Whereas <hi>Argantonius</hi> may be ſaid to have died young, tho' he lived an hundred and twenty years, becauſe he was remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able only for his Age. Tis like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58560:29"/>to be noted, that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all notable men have died in their youth. <hi>Hercules, Achilles, Caſtor, Pollux, Ajax, Jaſon, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, Catullus, Tibullus, Virgil, Demoſthenes, Cicero, Julius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Severus, Alexander, Probus, Aurelian, Claudius,</hi> died all of 'em young: <hi>Who were too great and too good for this World,</hi> and <hi>therefore the Gods took 'em to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">XIV. But put caſe thou liveſt to be old, how many vexations muſt thou expect, what infirmities, Weakneſs, Maladies, Rhumes, Catarrhs, beſides, the ſeeing of thy ſelf avoided and loathed by every body: Thou art tireſom even to thine own Children, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſom to thy ſelf, troubleſom
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58560:29"/>to thy Friends, and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thy Servants. Thy Taſte is gone, reſt thou canſt not, and being burdenſom to thy ſelf, how canſt thou but be burdenſom to others. We read that <hi>Zeno</hi> the Philoſopher, when he could not get rid of his life by Age, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled himſelf. What pains and art was <hi>Tully</hi> fain to uſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade people to bear their Old age. Whereas no man thinks it neceſſary to exhort men patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to endure Health, or Riches: I am extremely taken with that ſaying of <hi>Theraminis,</hi> who only eſcaping out of a ruin'd Houſe, and his Friends congratulating his good hap, cries out, <hi>O Fortune, for what ſadder chance doſt thou reſerve me!</hi> What he ſaid was
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58560:30"/>not without reaſon, for not long after he ſuffered a painful death by the cruelty of Tyrants. <hi>What man that has lived to be Old, if proffered to live over again his paſt time, would accept of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> And ſeeing Old men can expect nothing but Crazineſs, Coughs, Conſumptions, Cares and uneaſineſs; I ſee no cauſe why they ſhould deſire to live. And if when we are young and enjoy the full uſe of our ſenſes, beauty, ſtrength, wit and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we are oft weary of our life, what ſhall we do when we hear (if we have any hearing left) our ſelves called Old-doating-fool, and be made the ſubject of mens laughter and pity.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58560:30"/>XV. Art thou troubled to <hi>dye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone and leave ſo many behind thee? Remember to what a great company thou art going, and that thoſe whom thou haſt left alive muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty follow thee, and that ſo ſpeedily that they may be ſaid to dye with thee and bear thee company.</hi> The Fates are always at work, ſuffer none to tranſgreſs their limits: This is an unalterable Law, <hi>Tis appointed for all men once to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">XVI. And as amongſt Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perſons, thoſe that have been leſs Criminal, are firſt diſpatched, whereas the others who have been guilty of greater crimes, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved laſt to behold the terrors of death: So God firſt takes away thoſe whom he loves; to prevent their being the ſad wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58560:31"/>of others Miſeries. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member when I was but a Child, my Mother <hi>Clara Michera,</hi> then a Young Woman, was notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding wont to wiſh ſhe had dyed in her Infancy: when Older, ſhe ſtill continued to ſay the ſame; I Askt her the reaſon, whereto ſhe replyed, I live in expectation of Death, which could not have been ſo troubleſome in my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, being then unſenſible what it was to live or dye.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. There is nothing but brings greater ſorrow with it than joy, for pleaſure when gone, is ſucceeded by ſadneſs. <hi>What do we Live for, to Eat and Drink, and talk of News, and do the ſame things over and over again?</hi> What is there in this Life that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58560:31"/>daily trouble to dreſs and undreſs a mans ſelf: <hi>Whereas the dead feel neither Cold in Winter, nor Heat in Summer, Cares and Fears come not near them, for in the Grave the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and there the weary be at reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. Tis ſaid of the <hi>Galatians</hi> that they ſo little regarded death, that they choſe to fight Naked. The Gymoſophiſt anſwered <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> very ingeniouſly, who being askt by him which was ſtrongeſt, Life or Death, replyed Life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it bears ſo many Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. Were it not for death, what a Cage of ravenous birds would this World be? men would only meditate and improve their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58560:32"/>Arts of Violence and Oppreſſion, ſeeing in this ſhort time they Live, and within ſight of Death, they are guilty of ſuch Enormities.</p>
               <p>Again, how needful is it that good men may thereby receive the reward of their vertues, and live amongſt ſuch bleſſed Spirits as inhabit above the moon and ſtars. So that Death can be only terrible to wicked men, who are to be tormented in dark and ſolitary places.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. Some men are troubled about the manner of their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, a fooliſh care, and not to be compared to that pleaſant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of good <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who lying Sick and like to dye under a Tree, Anſwered them that askt him how he would be Buried, that <hi>they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58560:32"/>ſhould let him lye where he was:</hi> to which they replyed, the Beaſts would tear him in pieces; prithee ſays he, then, lay a ſtick by me that I may drive 'em away: Nay ſay his Friends, that will be to no purpoſe when you ſhall be ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; to whom he again replys, <hi>What harm can they then do me?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The death of Parents, Children and Relations not to be Lamented. Remarkable Examples of ſuch as have born them patiently.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. HAving ſaid thus much touching our own deaths, come we now to conſider what
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58560:33"/>reaſon we have to Lament the death of others, whom we Love. We mourn either in reſpect of our ſelves or them; if for them, we believe their Souls are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal or immortal; if mortal, then we thus Complain: <hi>O Alaſs, henceforth thou ſhalt be no more thirſty, hungry, cold, hot, naked, ſick, lyable to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and vexations, yea that which is more, thou art no longer lyable to death as I am.</hi> Or if thou believeſt the Soul to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, then muſt thou thus Lament. <hi>Alaſs my dear Friend (or Child,) thou art of a mortal Creature become an immortal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of a miſerable Wretch, an happy Soul, thou haſt paſſed from death to Life, from a Vale of Tears,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58560:33"/>to a Place of Inexpreſſible Joy.</hi> Who can hold his ſides in hearing thee thus Complain? But if thou ſay I Lament my own Loſs, then thou ſheweſt thy ſelf an Envious and Narrow Soul, in deſiring to detain him in Miſery, and deprive him of thoſe Joys he poſſeſſes, on Account of ſome little Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages thou receiveſt by his Company.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Beſides, conſider tho' thou haſt loſt thy good Friend, yet has he left behind him him as good men as himſelf. But ſuppoſing thou ſhalt never light of the like, yet remember what pains thou haſt taken for him when living, how burdenſome he has been to thee, and how uncertain thou art of his good will towards thee,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58560:34"/>and what he might at length ſhew'd himſelf to thee had he lived longer. How commonly have men been injur'd, yea ruin'd by their own kinſmen, brethren and relations, by whom heretofore they have been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi> helped <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Ceſar</hi> to fight againſt his Countrey; but being made Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, they ſlew him. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> while he Lived was faithfully ſerv'd by his Soldiers, but when dead, his children, kindred, and friends, were all deſtroyed by them, and yet at the death of one of them, he felt ſuch grief, that he ſcarcely could ever forget it.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The <hi>Thracians</hi> at the death
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58560:34"/>of their friends were wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and make good cheer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conſidered them as delivered from all wordly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and arrived at felicity. And on the contrary, when any Child was born, they wept and lamented its entrance into a troubleſome world: which cuſtom a Citizen of ours follow'd, who dying, deſired, that with muſick and dancing he might be carried forth to his Burial.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Wiſe and diſcreet Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, in complyance with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Folly, appointed limits to Mourning. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> gave leave for a man to Lament Eleven Days, but after that he muſt be no longer ſeen to Lament.</p>
               <p n="5">V. When thou Lamenteſt the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58560:35"/>Death of thy Friend, tell me whether thou hadſt rather dyed thy ſelf? Thus it muſt needs be, either Children muſt dye before their Parents, or Parents before their Children, or elſe all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But to dye all together is eſteemed a great Calamity. Do'ſt thou mourn becauſe thy Friend or Child is delivered from Old Age? Or do'ſt thou Lament that in others, which in thy ſelf thou thinkeſt ought patiently to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. Or wilt thou weep like the Old Woman I knew, who coming to the Gate where we were, begg'd Alms, and the more to move us to Compaſſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, She was without Father or Mother, whereupon we asked what Age ſhe was of, ſhe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58560:35"/>a Poor Old Woman of above Fourſcore, which made us all burſt out into Laughter, for although we pity'd her Age, yet we could not be much concern'd at the loſs of her Parents.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. 'Tis reported that in the Iſland of <hi>Coius,</hi> the Old Men being paſt Threeſcore, are wont to be carryed in Triumph thro' the City, and afterwards ſlain in the ſight of all the People. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe after that Age, they being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, their deaths in reſpect of the want of Proviſion, may great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly benefit the Common-wealth. The Country of the <hi>Caſpians</hi> abounding with men, but ſcarce of Proviſion; their Cuſtom is, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Parents be paſſed Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and Ten, to ſhut 'em up and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58560:36"/>ſtarve them with hunger, which is indeed Cruel and Barbarous, but when Natural Death hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to our Parents, we ought pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to bear their Loſs, in as much as they have run through their Courſe of Miſery, whereas we are to abide the troubleſom Aſſaults of it.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Yet would I not Counſel thee to do as a Young Man did who claimed Kindred of us; for he, when he was told his Father was dead, fell a dancing in the preſence of ſeveral People, and cryed out 'twas pity he dyed not ſooner: but the wretch eſcaped not unpuniſhed for his impiety, and breach of the precept, for he dyed of a Conſumption ſoon after. Not only <hi>Moſes,</hi> but even
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58560:36"/>
                  <hi>Homer</hi> affirms thoſe to be ſhort-lived, that do not render their Parents the reſpects due for their Education. But as tis the temper of an ungracious Son to wiſh the death of his Parents, ſo it is the part of a wiſe Son patiently to bear it. And in like manner the loſs of other Relations; haſt thou loſt thy Brother, experience ſhews us, that moſt brothers be quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, cumberſom, envious, capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and diſdainful. The Poet was wont therefore very wel to <hi>reſemble Brethren to the winds, becauſe they ever diſagree,</hi> and live as if they were born for no other end (in reſpect of each other) but to quarrel. <hi>Cain</hi> gave us an early Specimen of what Brotherly Love would be. Then <hi>Jacob</hi> deceived
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58560:37"/>
                  <hi>Eſau, Abſalom</hi> kills his Brother <hi>Amnon, Abimelech</hi> the Son of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon,</hi> murdred his Threeſcore and Nine Brethren, leaving only One alive. It would be an endleſs Task to recite all the Miſchiefs which one Brother has done another. I knew one man that killed his Two Brethrne at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times; Another the Year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was Beheaded for having murdred Three of his Brethren. But admit thy Brother be a good Man: yet what benefit canſt thou expect from him more than others? if thou wanteſt Aſſiſtance, a Friend, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, is better than a Brother, if thou expects Love, it muſt be from thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; if Obedience, from thy Son; if Flattery, and Obſequiouſneſs, from thy Servant.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58560:37"/>VIII. But thou wilt Reply, I loved my Brother dearly: but did he love thee? <hi>Alexius</hi> was Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Iſaac</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> by whom he was not only redeemed out of Slavery from the <hi>Turks</hi> with a conſiderable Sum of money, but alſo admitted to ſhare with him in the Government of the Empire; notwithſtanding which great kindneſs, he not only a while after his return, depoſed <hi>Iſaac</hi> from his Kingdom, but put out his Eyes and kept him in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Impriſonment.</p>
               <p>Thou mayeſt boldly ſay thou loveſt, and not be deceived, but canſt not know how thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved thy ſelf. Thou weepeſt for him, who had he ſurvived, would not have ſhed one Tear
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58560:38"/>for thee. If thou wert unwilling to dye before him, why doſt thou lament that he is firſt dead. Is it not ſufficient for thee to believe he is gone to Heaven, or art thou ſorry he has obtained liberty, and everlaſting life.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. The death of Children ſeems indeed a ſad Affliction, and in a manner inſupportable, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if a man has none left, and all hope of having more cut off. Yet let us conſider whether he is more happy that is barren and has no Children, or the other? The Childleſs man has only to lament his want of Poſterity, which if thou deſireſt in reſpect of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity, thou fooliſhly hopeſt that amongſt ſo many thouſands of men, thy Poſterity ſhould remain,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58560:38"/>tho' the world were never to end? But that the World will end, all Authority grants unleſs it be that of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But if thy Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity do always remain, art thou ever a whit the happier for that? So ſubtil a thing is this pleaſure of Poſterity, as indeed it may be called nothing; for after a few years all memory of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors is worn out. <hi>Who is he that ever knew almoſt his great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father?</hi> Whereas on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſo ſmall a pleaſure how great care is joyned? Hence comes danger of death, charge of their education, fear of want, care for their learning, wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in childhood, raſhneſs in youth, ſtubborneſs, diſobedience and pride, eſpecially in thoſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58560:39"/>whoſe Parents are rich. <hi>Compare the life of thoſe that have not Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with thoſe that have, and thou ſhalt ſoon find a vaſt differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi> The former live compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively without care, free, jocund, and lively: fear neither Poverty nor Riches, publick nor private Calamity. In times of Famine, War, or Peſtilence a good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured Man's mind is wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for his Children and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. In time of Plague, thou haſt no place to flee to, in times of War thou canſt not remove. In times of Famine unprovided whither to go.</p>
               <p>Conſider well theſe incumbrances and ſee whether they are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the want of Children.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58560:39"/>X. Again, Why art thou troubled at the loſs of Children? As for thy Childes part, thou haſt no reaſon to lament, who either feeleth nothing, or elſe is in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible felicity: And as to thy ſelf, thou haſt changed dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for ſecurity, labour for reſt, bondage for liberty, and yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineſt? Not long ſince I heard ſome poor Women lamenting and wiſhing the death of their Children. Had it not been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them to have had none than thus to wiſh their deaths? Take this for a certain truth, <hi>if thou art poor, thou canſt have no comfort in Children:</hi> and he that is Rich, what ſecurity hath he of continuing ſo?</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58560:40"/>
               <p>But thou haſt loſt thy Child? And cannot that loſs be ſupplied? tis true, the death of thy Father or Brother cannot be repaired.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Thou wilt ſay perhaps, My Son was now become like unto me, I had ſpent much money, care and pains upon him, and probably might have hapned to be a brave Fellow. But theſe complaints better become the Women; for if thou bewaileſt thy loſs of Money, then thou hadſt more need be cured of thy covetouſneſs, than comforted for the loſs of thy Son: Beſides, the better he was, the fitter for Heaven, and the greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon haſt thou to be comforted at his departure; for had he ſtaid longer here in the world, ſo great
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58560:40"/>and bewitching are the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof, that thou haſt great reaſon to fear his being ſtruck with the contagion of bad examples. Whereas now he has eſcaped the Vices of the age, and gone to the place of innocent Souls to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thoſe divine pleaſures which are too big to be deſcribed; unto which felicity he could not arrive but by death. He has paid that debt which is due to Nature, and gone to the Grave where thou muſt ſoon follow. <hi>Weep for thy ſelf then, not for him, for his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is over, whereas thine is to come.</hi> I muſt confeſt Nature do's ſtrongly impoſe upon us in this caſe, otherwiſe we could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſo much as we do the love of our ſelves, our Country, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58560:41"/>both to God and Man. So do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly fond are we of 'em, as ſhews in effect we rather hate them. We indulge them in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, eaſe and wantonneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, pride and covetouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. Nature cannot be blamed as enduing us with this fooliſh care and immoderate love; for the appetites ſhe has implanted in us are modeſt and limited; and if we paſs the bounds, tis not Her fault. Other creatures eat and drink only when neceſſity urges them, whereas Man do's this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably and wantonly. Being guilty of the ſame immoderation herein, as in the love of his Off-ſpring; not valuing what becomes of his own Body or Soul provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he can leave them rich.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58560:41"/>XIII. This extreme affection is not according to Nature, but a Vice. Behold other living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures when they have brought forth their young into the world, and find them able to ſhift for themſelves, take no farther care of them: In this far happier than Men. Let the examples of the Wiſe moderate thy grief. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> made a Funeral Oration for his own Son, wherein he prais'd him for his vertues, and ſo buried him. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the 7th. day after the death of his only Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put on his white Garment, was Crowned, and Sacrificed an Ox. <hi>Dion</hi> fitting in Council up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on publick affairs, and informed his only Son had fallen from the Houſe-top and broke his Neck,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58560:42"/>gave order for his Burial, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued on his buſineſs. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>Pericles</hi> is to be admir'd, for having loſt within eight days his two Sons, young men of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great hopes, did notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding put on his white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was Crown'd, made Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from his Houſe where his Children lay dead, delivered his advice upon ſundry weighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and diſcourſed at large touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the art of War. So <hi>Anaxago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> whilſt he was diſputing with his Scholars, word was brought that his Son was dead, whereat he paus'd a while, and returned anſwer to the Meſſenger, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd he had begotten a Mortal Creature. When <hi>Brutus</hi> openly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58560:42"/>puniſhed his two Sons, what ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror did this ſtrike into his Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, what fear into his Enemies, and admiration into his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? For that inſtance of his Juſtice and Severity, did mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advantage the Empire and ſtir up all Counties round about it to the emulation of ſo great a virtue.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. Neither doth Story on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniſh us with inſtances of Mens heroick courage in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, but alſo of Womens. <hi>Cornelia</hi> the Mother of the <hi>Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi,</hi> of many Sons having only two left, and they both ſlain, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the reciting the worthy deeds of them and their Father,) did not make any other ſhew of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. <hi>Argilon</hi> the Mother of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,</hi> the <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> King,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58560:43"/>hearing her Son was ſlain, gave no ſign of Grief, but Askt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he Nobly and Worthily Dyed. Another when word was brought her of her Sons being Slain, Was it not neceſſary, ſays ſhe, that he ſhould ſlay others, or be ſlain himſelf? I could give a Thouſand inſtances of this kind, were it neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58560:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The unprofitableneſs of Riches. A brief Account of the Authors Life. Poor men more happy than Princes. No man poor that has whereon to Live.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. MOſt mens minds are ſo greatly ſet on Riches, that till Death comes they think of nothing elſe. For every man fancies he has a long time to live, and puts the Evil Day far from him, <hi>as if the forgetfulneſs of that time were a means to eſcape it.</hi> And not contented with this, they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem all men fools that purſue not the ſame Ends. As if Riches could deliver from Death, or were of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58560:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>any value to a Man in the Grave. Rather ought we to conſider we are to paſs over into thoſe parts, whither we can carry nothing with us, but our Vertues or Vices: for whenſoever thou ſhalt dye, will come into thy remembrance not thy wealth, but thy grievous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, not thine honor or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but thy faith and hopes of mercy. <hi>For at that inſtant all things will ſeem to thee to be anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated, and thy diſturbed fancy will imagine the whole world to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into its former confuſion. And as the Land ſeems to move in the ſight of ſuch as ſail on the Sea in a Ship, ſo in the hour of death will all things ſeem to paſs away.</hi> when thou ſhalt for ever take leave of this earthly life, never
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58560:44"/>more to return to thy friends, wealth or pleaſures, in which thou haſt ſo greatly truſted. Therefore if thou expecteſt any other life after this, why doſt thou not ſpend thy time in Vertue? But leſt I be thought to give that counſel to others which I never had occaſion to uſe my ſelf; know that I alſo have been in miſery; and therefore expect to be the more credited.</p>
               <p n="2">II. I was born in a time of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, when my Mother being big with Child of me, was forced to leave the City; half dead came I into the world, in the year 1501, when all men deſpairing of my life, by vertue of a Bath made of Wine, I was recovered. Within three months after I loſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58560:45"/>two of my Brethren and one Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. The Plague continuing in our City, took away my Nurſe: whereupon I was charitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the houſe of <hi>Iſiodorus Reſta</hi> a noble Gentleman and friend of my Father, where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a few days I fell ſick of a Dropſy and Flux of the Liver, yet nevertheleſs preſerved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the wrath or mercy of God, I know not. There was no kind of diſtemper which I did not undergo till I attained eight years of age. At which time, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Servant to my Father, and ſo continued till I was eighteen.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Thus did I paſs the flower of my youth, both without delight and ſtudy. At length perceiving I could not compel nor perſuade
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58560:45"/>my Father to give me Learning, I intended for love of it, to enter into ſome Religious houſe. My Mother ſeeing her want of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, intreated my Father to put me to School, where, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring my time already loſt, and the ſhortneſs of Mans life, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed my ſelf to my Book, ever in fear leſt my Father hearing ſome bad report, ſhould take me away.</p>
               <p>I was not a little perplexed with the difficulty of the <hi>Latine</hi> Tongue, but having with much labour maſtred the uneaſy part thereof, my Father gave me leave to ſtudy <hi>Geometry</hi> and <hi>Logick,</hi> in which I made ſome proficiency. Then diſtance from my Father making him begin to love me, he
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58560:46"/>died, having newly begun to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect me. At that time the Wars began in our Country, when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor and void of all other help, through the great care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of my Mother I was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, when my ſmall Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was not ſufficient; for ſuch as it was I ſpent it in the office of Rector in the Univerſity: Nor had I any other way of getting my living but by playing at Cheſs.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. At length after I had rub'd through ſeveral ſtraights, I ſetled my ſelf and Family in the Town of <hi>Pavia,</hi> where by practice of Phyſick, tho' poorly, I made a hard ſhift to maintain my ſelf and Family; for I had contracted debts by my vain-glorious office. Then my Mother ſends for me
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58560:46"/>home to the City, where I found all things in diſorder as to my private affairs, no friends, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, my Kinſmen ſued me at Law; and was refuſed in our College of Phyſicians, <hi>being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected a Bastard</hi> becauſe my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſed me ſo ill. Neither can I boaſt of any favour from the Phyſicians of <hi>Padoa,</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving twice deſerved to be made Doctor, they denied me my Grace. But at length through the earneſt ſuit of the Preſident, I took that degree. This might well ſhame me to relate, were not their injuſtice the cauſe, not my want of Learning.</p>
               <p>Not long after this I fell into a Conſumption, a diſtemper which many Phyſicians hold incurable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58560:47"/>Yet it pleaſed God I eſcaped it after ſeven Months without help of any Phyſician, and beyond all expectation. Let any one now imagine what cares, ſorrow and vexation my mind endured, when on the one ſide I conſidered mine own great poverty, and on the other, my Mothers unwieldy and helpleſs age. Beſides this, the oppoſition of my Relations, the wrong received from the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, the threatnings of a Great Man, the deſpair of Health, want of Friends, and an Houſe to lie in, did all together beſet me. I needed whereon to live: Labor I was not able, and could not think of begging, were my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities never ſo great. Yet at length notwithſtanding theſe manifold
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58560:47"/>vexations by returning to the City, I recovered my Health, met with Friends who comforted and bountifully relieved me.</p>
               <p>My Phyſick in my ſickneſs was Abſtinence. Againſt my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes I made uſe of Patience, againſt Poverty, Sparingneſs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Proſecution diligence to avoid the ſtrokes of it; againſt Repulſes the precepts of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy; and from the beginning of my troubles (this Book tho' not then written) did greatly comfort me.</p>
               <p>Being thus returned to my Country, my Mother at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered her health, and was my ſelf relieved and defended by my good Patron the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Philip Archintus,</hi> both for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58560:48"/>Vertue and Learning an excellent Man. Afterwards through the aſſiſtance of <hi>Alphonſus D'Avila</hi> (to whom I Dedicated my Book <hi>De Aeternitatis Arcanis</hi>) I was admitted one of the College of Phyſicians, with the good liking of every honeſt man, being then almoſt Forty years of age.</p>
               <p>Such hath been the courſe of my Life: what helps my Studies have contributed to the mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſundry hardſhips there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, any man may imagine. As for Riches I ever contemned them, with the ſame greatneſs of mind, as all other chances of Fortune; Patience in all the occurrences of my whole Life has extremely hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me: for by vertue thereof I have found aſſiſtance in my great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58560:48"/>extremity, even from them of whom I have leaſt deſired or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected any thing; for <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Bonafidus,</hi> an able and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſician, ſo ſtoutly defended my Cauſe againſt the Doctors of <hi>Padoa,</hi> as no Brother for a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could do more.</p>
               <p>Great aſſiſtance did I alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Francis Cruceirs,</hi> a moſt upright Lawyer, my Suit depending in the City of <hi>Milain,</hi> who greatly encouraged me to proceed in this my preſent Work, as well as in others, but I have found that to the writing of Books, a Mind free from ſuch troubles as I have ſuffered, is abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite.</p>
               <p>But I have ſaid too much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps touching my ſelf. Yet what
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58560:49"/>honor and credit can baſe Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage be, the ſlightings of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Friends, and Country, my want of Health, and Poverty, next to Beggary? Whoſoever thinks I have ſpoken this out of Vain-glory, muſt repute me a very Fool. But it was my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign by my own Example to teach theſe two things. Firſt, that tis nothing but a guilty Conſcience can make any man miſerable. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that conſtancy of Mind do's greatly help, not only to bear Evils, but to procure a change of Fortune. But however <hi>this is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to keep thee from being mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, to believe thou art not ſo.</hi> Which Rule in one word may be taught and learned of every man.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. But I promiſed at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58560:49"/>of this Book to treat of Poverty and its Remedy: For the Burden of it ſeems to ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, as it was obſerv'd of old by <hi>Menander.</hi> In diſcourſing of which, we ſhall firſt conſider, That the Poor man is no leſs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py than the Rich. Secondly, that Poverty is no hindrance to the atchieving glorious Actions. And Thirdly, that there's nothing more hurtful to a poor man than to deſire to be rich. Fourthly, that Riches after death do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profit the deceas'd, nor his Poſterity.</p>
               <p n="5">V. As to the Firſt, I affirm there is greater felicity to be found in a poor Commonwealth than in a rich; leſs hatred, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and diſorder. <hi>Pliny</hi> oft
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58560:50"/>mentions the reſpect which the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> gave the <hi>Romans</hi> for their Vertue, altho' at Wars with them: But when once Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches grew in Credit, nothing continu'd ſtable, nothing quiet; the People always at variance, the Senate without authority, Laws violated, Gravity and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety ridicul'd and laught out of countenance, all things profan'd and mixt with the dregs of Slaves and Strangers. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that <hi>Miſery is an attendant of Riches, and Quietneſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. But to paſs by Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, let us turn our Diſcourſe to private perſons, whoſe Lives are far more happy than thoſe of Princes and great Perſons; for
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58560:50"/>what proof of Friendſhip can they receive, when hope of Reward, or fear of Puniſhment are the motives that influence all about them. And therefore King <hi>Philip</hi> reproved his Son <hi>Alexander,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thought to gain the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will of his people by Liberality. But ſuppoſing they were in this particular equal to private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, let us conſider whether their Lives in other matters are to be compared, inreſpect of happineſs, with them. The Poor Man ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing early; after his Hands be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, betakes himſelf to his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, at which having for ſome time exerciſed himſel (beſides the help of his hungry Supper) the night before with his fellow-laborer, they ſavor all ſorts of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58560:51"/>Meat, whatſoever cometh to hand ſeemeth pleaſant, delicate and precious. At Dinner they diſcourſe of jocular matters, and talk what hope they have of time to come. This company breeds no Diſcontent, this diet cauſeth no Satiety, no Diſdain, no Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. The Dinner ended, after pauſing a while, they return to accuſtomed labour, by which they get a good appetite to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: there being met, they want no mirth, gentle Jeſts, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Tales, according to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Gueſts. Then to Bed they go, whereunto preparing themſelves, the ſhining Stars put them in mind to look up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to that moſt bleſſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey where they hope at length
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58560:51"/>to arrive. If conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of any amiſs word or deed, they implore the Divine Forgiveneſs: and being wearied with hard labour, the Good man ſoon falls into a ſound ſleep. Thus do's he enjoy Health and a long Life, neither troubled at what's paſt, nor afraid of what's to come.</p>
               <p>On Holy days, he reſteth his wearied Limbs: Then wanders at will, and if there be any thing in City or Country pleaſant and worth ſeeing, he may without offence behold it. He veiws the Suburbs, green Fields and ſmiling Meads, meets his Companions, and every where takes his diſport. No vexatious thoughts hinder the tranquillity of his mind, but joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in Life, and lives prepared
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58560:52"/>for Death: and if he chance to be ſo learn'd that he can read Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, he may be accounted ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the more happy.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Whereas the life of a Prince is quite contrary; for he having with much difficulty got off yeſterdays Surfeit, gets up, his Mouth not well in taſt, and troubled with the nauſeous bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his own Stomach, is ſo uneaſie that he knows not what to do with himſelf. Then his Guard comes about him, Soldiers, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Paraſites, Flatterers, and Suiters; People ſwarm, cry out and complain; the Porters keep back the importunate Gueſts, and ſome (and they perhaps the moſt troubleſom) for Money are let in. And if the Prince be a man of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58560:52"/>buſineſs, he examines his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, which finding to be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, he loaths his own life; for ſome things he deſpaireth to bring to paſs; and others he hopes not without difficulty to effect. Now he blameth the unfaithfulneſs of ſome perſons: Then accuſeth the negligence of others. At laſt he finds all his Friends and Servants are friends to their own intereſt, and ſerve him only to ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Now is his mind perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how to provide againſt ſuch an imminent danger. Then he goes to Chappel. Afterwards hears Suits, wherein the more attentive he is, the more is his trouble and anxiety of mind; ſo at laſt he refers all to his Council.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Then comes Dinner-time,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58560:53"/>when he has Diſhes, Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Cups, Saucers, Carpets, Wine, Sallets, Sauce, Meat, Bread, and all ſorts of Dainties; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſetled at Meat, either he has no Company at all, or if any, they be his inferiors, who are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to gape for every bit of Meat he puts in his mouth; whereas he having no appetite, and being us'd to theſe delicacies, they do not at all pleaſe him, neither takes he delight in any thing he ſees; aſham'd at his own faſtidiouſneſs, he looks here and there, and at length chooſes ſomething that is leaſt diſpleaſing to him. But ſuppoſing this day brings him a Stomach, which is very rare, do's he then receive any ſatisfaction? none at all, for he is ſuſpicious
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58560:53"/>and fearful of every thing, Meat, Drink, Cups, Napkins, Trenchers and Knives may be Poyſon'd. What pleaſure can there be in Eating, to a man beſet with ſo many fears? <hi>were it not better to eat butter'd Parſnips and Turnips in an Earthen-platter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">IX. When <hi>Damocles</hi> had long flatter'd <hi>Dioniſius,</hi> the Tyrant cauſed this Paraſite to put on his Princely apparel, placed him in his Chair of State, and ſet before him all the Riches of <hi>Syracuſe;</hi> Which done, he by a ſmall Thread hanged over his head a ſharp na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Sword, which <hi>Damocles</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, durſt not ſtretch out his Arm, no nor endeavor to carve thoſe Delicacies which were ſet before him: But finding himſelf
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58560:54"/>on every ſide beſet with fear, pray'd his Hoſt to deliver him from this Royal Feaſt, by which he learned ſo much, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after deſired to become King.</p>
               <p n="10">X. Again, when a Prince has ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly Dined, and all his diſhes with great Ceremony taken away, then in come Jeſters, Juglers and Fidlers; ſome they craftily flatter, and others they diſgrace, whereat theſe laugh, the others inwardly fret and vex: in the mean time the Prince with feign'd chear, muſeth on matters more weighty; and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs calling him away, to Council he goes, where many matters be brought in queſtion, neither plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to hear, nor eaſie to effect; becauſe ſome of them are unjuſt, and others perillous. Now is he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58560:54"/>offended at his Miniſters admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and by and by diſcovers anothers Treachery; another's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude galls him, another's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes: His mind being thus vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he ſighs and laments, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to get rid of ſuch trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom thoughts, and thereupon betakes himſelf to diverſion: rides out of Town, but alas all in vain, for black cares ſit faſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him: and the worſt of it is, he can go no whither but the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple follow, and by the ſight of them, bring that to mind, which he cannot endure to think of. Then after diſcourſe of ſundry Matters, to Supper he goes, with the ſame Appetite he eat his Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and at length to Bed, where before he ſleeps, he ruminates on
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58560:55"/>ſundry unpleaſant matters, how many Men are or muſt be Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, tho' not juſtly, yet neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, what Secret practices are in hand againſt him, what War to be undertaken, and the manifold hazards of it; and on ſundry other anxious affairs, which make him at length think himſelf the moſt miſerable of all Mortals, and wiſh rather to have been born any thing than what he is. And thus paſſing from one fancy to another, he turneth and toſſeth his mind; and in the end finding all things vexatious and perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, deſireth Sleep, which is not eaſily had. But admit he do's ſleep, his reſtleſs Fancy is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ſuch unpleaſing imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, fearful Dreams and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58560:55"/>as ſurpaſs all deſcription. In a word, <hi>tho' his Bed be ſoft, rich and delicate, yet is his reſt oft-times hard and ſhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">XI. What is a Kingdom, ſays <hi>Antigonus,</hi> but a glorious Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? Kings are only the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Servants of many: Or if they be Lords over others, yet are they too oft Slaves to the vileſt luſts, inceſt, adulteries, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, murders, fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies; ſuſpect many times their neareſt friends, Children, Wife, Concubine, Cup-bearer, Barber; <hi>and what Guard ſo vigilant as can defend them.</hi> Whereas the Life of a poor man is void of all cares and fears, he lives long, is heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and vigorous.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. I remember but three men
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58560:56"/>that have paſs'd the age of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and they almoſt Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, one was a Carpenter, the other an Apothecary, and the third a Plowman. For how can his life be long that liveth in Luſt, Idleneſs, and Surfeitings; they are always idle, or exceſſively labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſitting up in the Night, and ſleeping in the Day; whence proceed Dropſies, Conſumptions, and Gouts, to the Rich: whereas you ſhall ſeldom hear a Poor man complain of it.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. 'Tis obſervable a Poor man has more beautiful Children than thoſe that be Rich, and are generally more fortunate: They frequently are barren, or if they have Children, they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very weak and ſickly; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58560:56"/>you ſhall never hear Poor men complain of the want of Iſſue, yea, are rather overſtockt. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Poor men enjoy that Liberty, which the Rich dare not pretend to. A man of a mean fortune can viſit every place, but Princes are withheld moſt times by Puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo's of Honor, and want of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to receive them. In Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, notwithſtanding the greateſt care, they are annoyed with Duſt; in Winter ſhun the Cold, and yet feel it. Whereas the Poor man in Summer works in the ſhade; and in Winter with labour expels the Cold by a moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous manner. The Rich man anxiouſly preſerves his Lands, which the Poor man beholdeth as well as he, and the ſeldomer he
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58560:57"/>has liberty to look abroad, the more pleaſure he has in ſeeing. I my ſelf for this very reaſon never wiſh'd to have Gardens in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs, as knowing other mens would be more pleaſant to me; <hi>and all the delight which we receive in theſe things is from their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and novelty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">XIV. All men endeavour to live, which living the Poor man obtains as well as the Rich; his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is healthful and vigorous, and mind beſt fitted for Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. The Rich man's mind is continually perplex'd with Cares, whereas the Poor man is only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to get his living. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe ſtudies how to keep his wealth, how to encreaſe and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58560:57"/>beſtow it. He is forced to keep others, and tho' called the Maſter of all, yet is he Servant to the whole family; his Life is many times in danger for his Riches: whereas the Poor man fears neither the loſing of his Life nor his Eſtate. One only fear the Poor man has, and that is, leſt he ſhould lack whereon to ſubſiſt; but yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, for being honeſt and induſtrious, ſhould he meet with any misfortune, there's no man but will be ready to help him: for ſuch a one cannot want Friends, the charity of Good men, and the aſſiſtance of Hoſpitals. <hi>I could never hear of an Honeſt man that was any conſiderable time in want.</hi> Its certain that <hi>Riches have killed more than Hunger.</hi> I
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58560:58"/>have known an hundred perſons my ſelf, whoſe great Eſtates have occaſioned their ruine; ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd by their Relations, others ſtabb'd, hang'd, robb'd and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as they were travelling; but I never knew above four that died of Hunger, and that by their own fault. Seeing then ſo few perſons periſh through Poverty, and ſo many by Riches, I pray which condition is moſt eligible. A Rich man is laden with unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Apparel, Houſhold-ſtuff, which require care in preſerving and daily reparation. Gold is no more wholſom to drink in than Glaſs, nor Silver more cleanly than Stone. Garments the more ſimple they be, the more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and leſs burdenſom. Man
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58560:58"/>is born Naked, he needs a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but no burden.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Socrates</hi> beholding great variety of Merchandiſes to be ſold in a Fair, how many things, ſays he, are there here of which I have no need? He eſteemed them likeſt the Gods that wanted few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt things. Coſtly Apparel is ſpoyled by Duſt and Moths; Water rots it, and Thieves ſteal it, or Neighbors borrow it. <hi>What is fine Attire but a burdenſom and troubleſom Bravery?</hi> In ſhort, what has a Rich man more than a Poor? The latter has Life, Health, Children, Meat, Sleep, Friends, Liberty, Security, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Reſt, with all other things needful. <hi>Lord, ſays the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, give me neither Poverty nor</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58560:59"/>Riches. And were a wiſe man left to his choice, he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prefer the former before the latter. Riches are more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than Poverty; for Poverty is relieved by art and induſtry, <hi>but there is no remedy againſt the diſcommodity of Riches.</hi> Alſo the fall from Riches is great and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recovery, whereas Poverty differs little from Sufficiency, and keeps a man out of danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. In Poverty at fartheſt, the Body can be only endanger'd, whereas Riches endanger the loſs of both Body and Soul. Finally, if Poverty be removed, all the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies wherewith 'tis attended be taken away. But ſuch as love Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, if they loſe them, do notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding keep ſtill thoſe vices and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58560:59"/>imperfections which they caus'd whilſt they poſſeſt them. Poverty is certainly worthy of great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for we are beholding to it for the inventions of Arts; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Rich men never deſerved this praiſe. <hi>Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle, Epictetus,</hi> and <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> were all poor men, the latter of which was fain all day to draw Water to get his living, and to Study in the night. <hi>Socrates</hi> was little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a Beggar. <hi>Plato</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came rich by his ſecond Voyage into <hi>Sicily. Ariſtotle</hi> lived a long time poor, and when an Old man, was enriched by <hi>Alexander. Homer</hi> that famous Greek Poet, was but a poor blind Harper. And <hi>Virgil</hi> the Prince of Latine Poets, was far from being over-rich. The
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58560:60"/>whole rout of Grammarians and Orators were ſuch kind of men: <hi>Pompilius, Andronicus, Orbilaus, Valerius, Cato, Laenius, Julius Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginus. Plinius Caecilius</hi> reports that <hi>Quintilian</hi> was not overſtockt with wealth. <hi>Juvenal</hi> mocking <hi>Statius</hi> the Fam'd Poet, tells us he begged his Bread.</p>
               <p n="18">XVIII. <hi>Paul Aemilius</hi> that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Captain could not make his Wife a Joynture. Alſo <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sextorius,</hi> came but of mean Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, yet one of them was the Terror, and the other the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of <hi>Rome. Scipio Africanus</hi> had lain in Priſon for debt, had not <hi>Gracchus</hi> aſſiſted him. <hi>Arator Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinatus, Calatinus Fabricius,</hi> that fought with <hi>Pyrus, Valerian, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicola, Menenius Agrippa, Q. Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58560:60"/>Ariſtides, Photion, Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiades, Cimon, Spartacus, Viria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> all the Dukes of <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> even the braveſt of them, as <hi>Liſander,</hi> came but of a mean Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. And whom can you alledge againſt theſe, the deſperate <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> or <hi>Ceſar</hi> the deſtroyer of his Countrey, or <hi>Scylla</hi> with his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions.</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. But to return to the Point in hand; what greater mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery can God lay upon a man, than to ſuffer him to covet Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: 'Tis Labour without end, and like the turning of <hi>Siſyphus</hi>'s Stone; who is ſaid, for revealing the Secrets of Heaven, to remain in Hell, and there continually to roll up a heavy Stone to the top of a ſteep Hill, which preſently
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58560:61"/>rolls down again, and he without ceaſing follows and brings it up upon his ſhoulders. For to what end doſt thou labour for more than will buy thee neceſſaries, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving thy ſelf of the comforts of what thou mayſt enjoy. Thou ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneſt thy days and hindreſt thy helth. Some men I have known live miſerably, to the end they might have a ſtately &amp; honorbale Burial.</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. But thou perhaps de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt not Riches upon this account, but to leave thy Son a fair inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance; ſo that thou laboureſt, ſtudieſt, watcheſt, hazardeſt the health of thy Soul and Body, doſt violence to thine own Conſcience, and deſtroyeſt the peace of thine own Mind, that thy Son may ſpend, conſume, make havock,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58560:61"/>Whore, Drink, Game, and Live in Riot and Idleneſs: To make him Proud, Soft, Ridiculous, Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Mad, and good for nothing. Again, How oft have we ſeen a great Fortune left to a Son or Daughter, make 'em a Prey to ſome greedy and perfidious Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain. In ſhort, <hi>Riches have been the cauſe of the moſt Bloudy and Tragical Events which we meet with in all Relations.</hi> Moſt of thoſe I ever heard of that by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance arriv'd to great Eſtates, have ſpent and conſumed 'em in a ſhort time. How can it but trouble thee when thou lyeſt upon thy death-bed, to think that what thou haſt gotten by great toyl, will ſerve only as a means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch thy Son. The Son of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58560:62"/>
                  <hi>Ruinus</hi> having received from his Father a rich inheritance, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a frenzy as coſt him his Life. How many ways are Laws violated? How many Rebellions happen! How many Treaſons, <hi>wherein ſuch as are of mean for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune are almoſt never concern'd.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, thou wilt leave thine Eſtate to a Son, or Brother, who proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly will not part with one Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it to redeem thy Life from the Grave.</p>
               <p>Yet ſuch is thy madneſs as with loſs of thine own quiet thou ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to make them Rich. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing Riches procure nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Glory nor Felicity to our Selves or Poſterity, there can be nothing more pernicious to us than to deſire 'em, and anxiouſly
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58560:62"/>purſue the ſearch of them. But here the Example of all the World will be objected againſt what I ſay, for every man ſeeks Riches, but no man wiſhes to be Poor. I ſhall not here ſet my ſelf to refute this Objection, only ſay in ſhort, that the Multitude are ill Judges of things, that they are the great Maſters of Error, and Enemies to all Philoſophy, that their Examples are in no wiſe to be imitated, they being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the wrong. For whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is profitable or neceſſary to any Creatures, that is naturally deſirable: in which deſires, bruit beaſts (who are guided only by Senſe) do not tranſgreſs. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as man who has moſt Reaſon in his Underſtanding, has leaſt in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58560:63"/>his Actions: for he Eats, Drinks, and Sleeps, more than either Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency or Neceſſity require: whatſoever more than neceſſary is deſired, is not only not good, but contrary to Nature. All men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſire Riches, as Meat or Drink, not becauſe Exceſs of them is natural, but becauſe ſomewhat in them is natural, that is to ſay, ſo much of them as ſerve to purchaſe Neceſſaries, which what man is he that does not get. For to have nothing, nor know which way to get any thing, is contrary to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>But it may be Objected againſt the Advantage which I alledged Poor men enjoy, ſuch as Labour, Exerciſe, Induſtry, Patience and Abſtinence, that theſe alſo may
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58560:63"/>be enjoyed by them that be Rich, and the choice of theſe being in the Rich Man, he is conſequently the moſt Happy. For if we wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly want pleaſure, the want of them cannot ſeem grievous. Yet herein is a great miſtake, becauſe that Man who has been gentily brought up, his mind is made effeminate, his body tender, and unable to endure Labour. He that has accuſtom'd himſelf to ſundry meats, his digeſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes delicate and ſqueamiſh: And if a man ſo Educated changes his dyet to poor mens fare, he ſoon becomes diſeaſed, full of obſtructions, and ſubject to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions. Or if he betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Labour, he grows thereby unhealthy, falls into feaveriſh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58560:64"/>and in a ſhort ſpace dyes. If ſuch kind of People, I ſay, as theſe, apply themſelves to hard ſtudy, they commonly ſhorten their days; as did <hi>John Picus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula.</hi> 'Tis rarely ſeen that a Man born to a great Eſtate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Excellent in Learning: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he at firſt liv'd meanly, or in his youth fell into ſome Frenzy. Again the Rich have more need of the Poor, than the Poor of the Rich. For the Rich Man needs a Phyſician, a Barber, a Groom, a Plow-Man, a Cook: and which of them needs a Rich Man?</p>
               <p n="20">XX. So great are the vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which attend Power and Authority, as will endear Poverty to a Conſiderative Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth tho' he Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58560:64"/>well and happily, yet how did the thoughts of preſerving his Empire diſquiet him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he was afraid that Sultan <hi>Solyman</hi> would invade the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of his Empire; otherwhiles he was perplexed how to preſerve the Iſlands of <hi>Baleares:</hi> Then he fears <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Pulia</hi> were not able to hold out againſt the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; each Province called for his Care, ſo that his thoughts were never at reſt. And ſhall we call him happy who was tormented with ſuch Anxieties? for my part I ſhould wiſh my ſelf rather a <hi>Carthuſian Monk,</hi> and undergo all the Severities of that Order, than to wear his Crown ſtuft with thoſe Cares: will any man ſay <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King might be called
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58560:65"/>happy, or Sultan <hi>Solyman?</hi> Alaſs which of 'em liv'd not in Fear? which of 'em lived free from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes? And tho perhaps they never met with any great miſhaps, yet conſidering what has befel others, and might befal them, they likewiſe may be ſaid to have ſpent their days in fearful expectations.</p>
               <p n="21">XXI. <hi>Polycrates</hi> who in his whole Life never met with any misfortune, was at length taken by the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> and hang'd. It were endleſs to recount the number of Kings whom Fortune has laughed at to ſcorn. Thou who admireſt the Life of Princes and Great Men, ſtanding gazing at their outſides, could'ſt thou but look into their breaſts, would'ſt heartily pity them, when thou
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58560:65"/>complaineſt of Poverty, do but <hi>conſider how many are poorer and miſerablie than thy ſelf, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of whom thou art Happy. How many be Sick? How many Deaf? Blind? How many in Priſon? How many in Exile? How many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to dye cruel and ignominious Deaths,</hi> than all which without doubt thou art more happy. Moreover, if thou complaineſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Poverty (unleſs thou wouldſt be a King) thou haſt no cauſe to lament. Behold how many live miſerably in the City? how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beg in the Suburbs; how many ſpend their days in the Countrey in extream want, yet burdened with Families and Children. <hi>How many poor Villages are there, that paſs joyfully their days in a mean
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58560:66"/>condition;</hi> becauſe they ſee none near 'em richer than themſelves: when as the ſame perſons if they reſort to the City, where they ſee the Riches and Bravery of others, then they repute themſelves miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and lament their hard fate. But this may be rather called En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy than Poverty. Should it come to paſs now as it did in the time of <hi>Noah,</hi> that all money, proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Cattel and other commodities, were carried away in a univerſal Floud: I believe then no man would think himſelf injured by Poverty. Why then doſt thou complain having whereon to live. This plainly evidences tis not Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty but Envy that moleſts thee, <hi>Why doſt thou not deſire the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Kings, and the Riches of</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:58560:66"/>India? How many Countries and People has Poverty ſubdued and preſerv'd. <hi>Alexander</hi> poſſeſſing nothing but Bodies and Weapons, Conquered all <hi>Aſia.</hi> The poor Common-wealth of <hi>Rome</hi> ſubdued the proud <hi>Gauls,</hi> the ſtately <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the crafty <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> the numerous <hi>Greeks,</hi> and the diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Jews.</hi> And by the ſame means the <hi>Germans, Perſians</hi> and <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> maintained their Rights, and kept their Liberties. But as ſoon as <hi>Scylla</hi> became Great, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced the Love of Riches, the Glorious Liberty of the <hi>Roman</hi> People melted away like Ice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sun: then followed Sedition, Civil Wars, and all manner of injuſtice and cruel Murthers, and in a ſhort time the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58560:67"/>whole Empire waſted to nothing.</p>
               <p n="22">XXII. Great Eſtates are ſeldom preſerved long in a Family. For we rarely ſee the Grandchild of a wealthy man dye Rich, which makes me the leſs mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail at ſo many great mens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining Riches. <hi>Crates</hi> the <hi>Theban</hi> ſo little valued them, that he caſt 'em into the Sea. <hi>Zeno</hi> having loſt his Eſtate, thanked God for that happy miſhap which made him a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. <hi>Diogenes</hi> not only pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently ſuffered Poverty, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Askt by <hi>Alexander</hi> what he wanted, replyed, <hi>Nothing:</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the bountiful offers of that great Prince. Which made him ſay, that if he were not <hi>Alexander,</hi> he would chooſe to be <hi>Diogenes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:58560:67"/>
            <head>CARDAN OF <hi>CONSOLATION.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">BOOK III.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Baniſhment, or Confinement.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THE next Calamity to Poverty is Baniſhment, and in this matter 'tis only Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that makes a man Miſerable: For how many men have meerly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58560:68"/>for Pleaſure, ſpent the greateſt part of their Lives in Travelling and viewing ſtrange Countries; as <hi>Plato, Beroſius, Galen,</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorides:</hi> and how many Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners amongſt us do the ſame for Profit. There was an <hi>Italian</hi> a Citizen of ours, who in Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Years had never travelled farthur than the Suburbs of the Town, which being told the Prince, he commanded that henceforward he ſhould not paſs thoſe bounds: The poor Old man diſliking this Confinement, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leave to travel in his Old age, which in his Youth he never mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which being deny'd, he fell ſick and died.</p>
               <p n="2">II. As for my part, I ſhould never value being Banniſhed my
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58560:68"/>own Country, provided I had whereon to live and maintain my ſelf and Family elſewhere: For a Man ſhall many times find more Civility and Reſpect abroad than at home.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Were Travail and leaving a Mans own Country to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned an Evil, why do ſo many Princes and great Perſonages vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily daily undertake it. To behold the different Situations of Cities, the various Cuſtoms, and manners of People, cannot but be exceeding grateful to the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Thou gaineſt hence Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and greater Reſpect when thou returneſt home. What plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſights do offer themſelves to thee, of Towns, Seas, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Rivers, Meads, Woods,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58560:69"/>Hills and Plains. <hi>Alexander</hi> is ſaid to Travel rather to excel <hi>Trajan,</hi> who envied his Fame, than from a deſire to Conquer the World.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. We find <hi>Homer</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his old Friend <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> for nothing more than for this. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Domeſthenes, Cicero, Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Thucidides, Themiſtocles, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades, Codrus, Theſeus, Eumol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Trax, Ariſtotle, Camillus, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialanus, Marius, Datanus, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibulus, Dion, Hannibal, Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius, Phalerius,</hi> have all been Banniſhed their Countries. <hi>Conon</hi> voluntarily Banniſhed himſelf into <hi>Cyprus, Iphicrates</hi> into <hi>Thrace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. In ſhort, Conſider again that of <hi>Socrates,</hi> the whole World is a Wiſe mans Country,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58560:69"/>and ſo long as ſuch a one is in the World, he is never out of it. Very pleaſant was the ſaying of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who being told that the Synopenſes had commanded him to forſake their Countrey: <hi>and I,</hi> ſays he, <hi>command them for ever to abide in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. Whoſoever performs any worthy Act at home, inſtead of Glory, gains only Envy. Where was our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected than in his own Country, being not only diſdained and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted there, but at length cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put to Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:58560:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Injuries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT perhaps thou wilt ſay, this is not my Caſe, thou art Wrong'd and Injur'd, and therefore defireſt Revenge. But pray conſider whither this courſe will lead thee, for he that ſeeks to revenge one injury, brings upon himſelf another: And he that offered the firſt injury with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out occaſion, what will he not do when provoked? Is it not better to be quiet, and conſider, that thy enemy being a bad Man, tis his nature to be doing Miſchief; and that he cares not whom he
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58560:70"/>hurts: That Vengeance belongs to God, and he will repay it. If thou haſt given a juſt Cauſe, blame not him, but thy ſelf, if not, it is the part of a Wiſe man to bear it patiently. When <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> was ſtricken upon the Shins and adviſed by his Friends to be revenged for that Affront, <hi>Shall I,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if an Aſs kicks me, kick him again?</hi> And when his Wife ſnatched his Cloak off his Shoulders, and his Friends per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded him to Chaſtiſe her: <hi>No, no,</hi> replyes he, <hi>tis ſufficient you know which is</hi> Socrates, <hi>and which is</hi> Zantippe.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>Diogenes</hi> receiving a box on the Ear, cryed out, <hi>Who thought I needed an Helmet, as oft as I go forth?</hi> So likewiſe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58560:71"/>
                  <hi>Crato</hi> being ſtricken on the Face by <hi>Nicodromo Citaredo,</hi> did no more, but wrote <hi>Nicodromo</hi>'s Name upon the Place, by which means he ſhew'd the whole City the Injury offered him. And <hi>Plato</hi> being told that <hi>Zenocrates</hi> Slandred him, ſaid firſt, <hi>He could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it;</hi> but when he was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it was ſo; Anſwered, <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think he would thus ſpeak without Cauſe.</hi> What could be more Nobly and Prudently ſaid.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. But we Chriſtians ought above all others to bear Injuries with Patience, following herein the Example of our Lord (the Founder of our Religion) <hi>who being Reviled, Reviled not again, and as a Sheep before his Shearers is Dumb, ſo he opened not his mouth.</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:58560:71"/>What a fooliſh thing is it to ſeek Revenge, when it cannot be had but with loſs to the Perſon injured. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> revenged himſelf on <hi>Philip,</hi> but was Hanged for it. So did <hi>Andrew Lampugnes</hi> upon <hi>Galeazeus Sforza,</hi> but thereby wrought, not only his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but alſo his whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Revenge for the moſt part more hurteth him that offers it, than him againſt whom it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: <hi>It oft ruines a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he has perfected it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">IX. When <hi>Cleomines</hi> had ſaid in the preſence of <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> that a man muſt do good to his Friends, and hurt to his Foes; he turned the words, ſaying, a man muſt benefit his Friends, and ſeek to be reconciled with his Enemies.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58560:72"/>
                  <hi>Greater by far is the pleaſure of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Injuries, than revenging them when it is in our power:</hi> for the Man that rendreth Good for Evil, is like unto God. <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> ſpared <hi>M. Marcellus</hi> his mortal Enemy; and ſet at liberty <hi>Petrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who was one of the Cheif that oppoſed him. He received into Favour <hi>Cato</hi>'s Son, whoſe Father was his unchangeable Adverſary. He Pardoned <hi>Ligarius</hi> at the ſuit of his Friends: He ſpared alſo <hi>Cicero,</hi> and freely forgave all other Princes that were in the Battel of <hi>Pharſalia.</hi> He ſet up the Images of <hi>Pompey,</hi> and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf ſo generous and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that <hi>Cicero</hi> both before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death affirmed, he deſerved better in point of Clemency than
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58560:72"/>
                  <hi>Pompey.</hi> How Nobly did <hi>Adrian</hi> mittigate his Paſſion; for being made Emperour, and meeting his Enemy, he ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt eſcaped:</hi> declaring that as before he wanted Power to be Revenged, ſo when he had it, he wanted Will.</p>
               <p n="10">X. 'Tis alſo to be conſidered there is nothing that more ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth Authority, than to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give and paſs by Injuries. And therefore <hi>Pelercus</hi> the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> complaining to his Brother, he was not ſo well beloved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Citizens as <hi>he</hi> was; he anſwered him, ſaying, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof is, <hi>Thou canſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Injuries.</hi> Tis likewiſe to be remembred that, <hi>all thoſe that aſpire to Greatneſs, do ever wink
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58560:73"/>at many Wrongs.</hi> Altho' <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great knew the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> hatred, and how zealouſly they Warred againſt him under <hi>Darius,</hi> yet he endeavoured not to be Revenged of them; which greatneſs of Mind <hi>Darius</hi> and others underſtanding, they of Foes, became his Faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Friends. Whereas had he given way to Paſſion, all the Flower of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Youth, yea, and all <hi>India,</hi> had ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt him; which would certainly have put a ſtop to his Projects. <hi>Pirrhus</hi> the Famous Captain took not the ſame courſe, for he yielding to his Fury, made his deſigns Abortive, and died in Miſery.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. When <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> was a
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58560:73"/>private man, he was much abuſed by <hi>Cajus Calvus,</hi> and <hi>Catullus;</hi> yet when he came to be Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he Wrote firſt unto <hi>Calvus,</hi> and Pardoned <hi>Catullus.</hi> Who was a greater Enemy to him than <hi>Clodius,</hi> who it was thought made him a Cuckold; yet when he was apprehended, he would not only not Condemn him, but ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him alſo from being Perjur'd: whereas <hi>Marius</hi> did otherwiſe, for he thirſting after the Blood of his Enemies, was not only in the proſecution of his Revenge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by them, but likewiſe his whole Family. When <hi>Fabius</hi> was conſtrained by the People, contrary to all Right, to admit of <hi>Minutius</hi> to be his Maſter of Horſe, and Equal, and in the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58560:74"/>Army, (who did ſeveral things contrary to <hi>Fabius</hi> his Deſires and his own Honour,) yet did the former forget all Animoſities, Joyned with him againſt <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> and ſaved him from exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great danger; which wrought ſo upon <hi>Minutius,</hi> that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed before all the People his unworthineſs to Govern, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Fabius</hi> to take upon him the Conduct of the whole Army.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. <hi>Cicero</hi> followed not this Example, when with cruel Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives he perſecuted <hi>Clodius,</hi> but for his pains, was himſelf Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. We diſdain the injuries done us by bruit Beaſts, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the wrongs offered by our Fellow-Creatures. We alſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58560:74"/>endure the injuries which Time do's us, and yet cannot bear the wrongs offered by Men; whereas we have greater reaſon to bear with the former, becauſe Man is our Companion in Life, and many times tho' we do not obſerve it, provoked by us.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. What a Noble Act was that of <hi>Lucius Murena,</hi> who threw his Gown over <hi>Cato</hi> and ſaved him from Death, who a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had accuſed him. <hi>Publius Pulcher</hi> being by the three <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuli</hi> charged with Inceſt, did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſave one of them from eminent Danger. The King <hi>Archelaus,</hi> when upon a time one threw Water upon him, and being perſuaded by them about him to inflict a grievous Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58560:75"/>upon him that did it, anſwered, <hi>I know he did not intend to caſt it upon me, but ſome body elſe.</hi> A Servant of <hi>Antius Reſtio's</hi> being long kept in Priſon by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters command, and often burnt with hot Irons, not only follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Maſter in a day of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, but alſo reſcued him from imminent Danger. <hi>There is no readier way to Honour, Safety, and Quiet, than to contemn Injuries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Altho the Dog be of far leſs uſe than the Ox or Horſe, yet is he more beloved of his Maſter, becauſe he patiently ſuffers from him all kinds of wrong: if you ſtrike them, they Fawn; if you drive them away, they return; if you chide, they flatter. And ſhall not we Men bear Injuries
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58560:75"/>upon a better account; <hi>be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient a while and thou ſhalt ſee thy wrongs revenged by Nature, by Chance, or by ſome other means;</hi> and he that with ſuch perplexity and hazard of thy ſelf thou ſought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to harm, ſhall without any danger on thy part be deſtroy'd. For the Lives of all ſuch as are diſturbers of publick Peace, are uſually of ſhort continuance.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. But that which moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Men is the injury they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from their Wives; a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous misfortune 'tis true, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry common. <hi>Pompey</hi> put away his Wife for Adultery, and <hi>Ceſar</hi> likewiſe his. The conſideration of which great Peoples miſhap, may ſerve to mitigate the ſowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thine. <hi>Septimius Severus,</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:58560:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:58560:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:58560:77"/>and <hi>Marcus Aurel. Antoninus</hi> had alſo diſhoneſt Wives, which did not at all diminiſh their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority among the People, or hinder them from living Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. For in reference to this matter, the fault lying in others, the diſhonour and infamy cannot redound to thee. A Citizen of <hi>Sparta</hi> finding a Man in Bed with his ill-favour'd Wife, cryed out, <hi>Alas unhappy Man, what neceſſity has drove thee to commit this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed deed. Salethus</hi> Prince of <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tona</hi> made a Law that Adulterers ſhould be burnt alive; yet when afterward himſelf was taken de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing his Brother's Wife, he made ſuch an ingenuous Oration, that the People were content to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58560:77"/>his offence only with Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yet being ſenſible of the greatneſs of his fault, he caſt himſelf into the Fire and dyed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſee he deſired not Pardon, (tho' his words ſeemed to require it,) but rather ſought to ſhew, that no offence could be ſo great but might deſerve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of Impriſonment.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUT we have ſaid enough of Injuries, Speak we now of Impriſonment, which ſeemeth the chief of all other Calamities: For in a Priſon is darkneſs, filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſolitarineſs, fetters, and all
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58560:78"/>other kind of Miſeries. But pray what is this life, but an impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Man's mind, much worſe than that of the Body. This would never ſeem any great Calamity to me, which ſo many excellent Men have (as it were) deſired. <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> to the end he might be forced to keep the Houſe, cut off one ſide of his Beard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A ſolitary life do's greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Contemplation, whereas Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hinders it.</hi> What place ſo fit for Study, as that where there is quietneſs. <hi>Boetius</hi> wrote no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better than what he wrote in Priſon. Did not <hi>Diogenes</hi> lurk a long time within a Tub? <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus</hi> ſeparated himſelf a great while from all Company, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:58560:78"/>voluntarily choſe remote corners, for the conveniency of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>Plato</hi> tells us that <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> while he remained in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wrote his Book <hi>de Circuli Quadratura.</hi> To whom could Impriſonment be more grievous than to <hi>Socrates,</hi> when it was to end in Death: yet did he ſleep quietly, ſtudied Philoſophy, and wrote Verſes. St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſent the greateſt part of his divine Epiſtles from Priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of Servitude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SErvitude ought patiently to be born, ſeeing Nature has not more liberally beſtowed her
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58560:79"/>gifts on the Maſter, than the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: they are equally Wiſe, Beautiful, and Healthful.</p>
               <p>As to Contentment, it is the Servant's fault if in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar he do's not outſtrip his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; for he has only one to ſerve, for which he has Meat, Drink, Apparel, and all other neceſſaries; Whereas a Maſter has not only himſelf to take care of, but alſo all others. <hi>Every Loſs is a hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the Maſter, but none to the Servant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are all Servants to one common Maſter, namely God Almighty, and ſhall be equally rewarded by him. What are Princes Favourites but Servants, tied to him by Ambitious hopes? Servitude can be no hinderance
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:58560:79"/>to vertuous and honourable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for <hi>Plato, Xenocrates, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius, Diogenes, Phaedrus, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus,</hi> and <hi>Aeſop,</hi> were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Such.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Sickneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. WHen Sickneſs is come upon thee, conſider that even this condition is not without its advantages; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou learneſt thy ſelf, that is to ſay, what a weak, poor and ſilly Creature thou art, who in health art ready to ſay with him in the Pſalms, <hi>tuſh, I ſhall never be moved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:58560:80"/>II. Now if thy Pains be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, they may be the more eaſily born; if extreme, they cannot laſt long. Sickneſs is as neceſſary as Food or Rayment, or any other of the things of this Life, which we cannot be without: 'Tis like Sawce, making us relliſh the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of health. As to the Pains and irkſomeneſs thereof, they are not comparable to what Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men endure in Child-birth; for neither Stone, nor Gout, nor Cholick, are like them: and yet do they ſoon forget 'um.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher being extremely Sick, ſaid unto one that came to viſit him, <hi>That the greatneſs of Pain ſhould never make him confeſs Sickneſs to be an Evil.</hi> For that which is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58560:80"/>without us cannot hurt us. <hi>If bodily pains do not conquer our Minds, they do us no harm.</hi> I remember when <hi>Antonius Cribel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> was condemned to be Torn in pieces, in preparing himſelf to be Executed, he ſaid, <hi>There was no Torment could make him diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Accomplices,</hi> altho' he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged he had ſuch. <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius</hi> ſhewed by holding his Finger to the Candle in ſight of the King, that there was no hopes of wreſting any thing from him.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Quintilia</hi> a little Woman being ſuſpected to be of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt <hi>Caligula,</hi> and Rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great torment, confeſſed nothing, and was therefore ſet at liberty as Innocent. What ſhould I
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:58560:81"/>ſpeak of St. <hi>Barbara,</hi> with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the number of which is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and their Conſtancy ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous, as they ſeemed not only patiently to have ſuffered Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but alſo to have wiſhed for them.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>The end of all Grief, either by Death or Recovery, becomes pleaſant.</hi> 'Tis alſo to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that all ſuch as ſuffer great Torments, being perſuaded of the Immortality of the Soul, ought therefore (were there no other reaſon) to be comforted. <hi>It is too much to puniſh both Body and Mind at one time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. In ſhort, Sickneſs puts us in mind of another life, it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders us ſober and thoughtful, and capable of hearkning to that good
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:58560:81"/>counſel, which when in Health we could not abide. Were it not for Sickneſs a Man would become more hard-hearted than a Tyger, and more cruel than a Lioneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP VI. <hi>Of general Calamities.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET us conſider whether in common Miſeries, we ought to lament? as in times of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Famine, and deſtruction of Countries; which being Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, make Men ſuffer them with leſs impatience: For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſeems diſhonorable that is common. But you'll ſay our Country is falling into Ruine,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:58560:82"/>and therein our Friends, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Eſtates: be it ſo. But doſt thou account only thoſe thy Neighbours, that inhabit thy Country? Surely we are all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from one Line, and if we look back to our great Grand-fathers, our Aſſinity is the ſame. And as to the loſing of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, perhaps they are but our hinderances to Vertue. <hi>There is nothing in this World can hurt any man but Vice. I am he,</hi> ſays <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes, upon whom all misfortunes are fallen; I have no Houſe, no Town, a Baniſhed Man, a Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond and Beggar.</hi> But he had a great Mind, which he thought of far more value.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Man's condition is like to a Garment, which the more rich
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:58560:82"/>and beautiful it is, the more do's a Spot fully it. 'Tis alſo to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that no Man is miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able all his life-time, for Sleep cauſeth forgetfulneſs of Sorrow, and is as pleaſant to thoſe in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, as thoſe that live at eaſe. Likewiſe the delights of our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, be to all men the ſame, as Taſte, Sight, Hearing and Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: So that all things which be delightful do not fail a Man at the ſame inſtant.</p>
               <p>Were all Mortals aſleep at the ſame time, then would none of them be more happy than his fellows. But we are certain not only all of us to ſleep, but to dye, and how ſoon, is to us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. <hi>Being once entred into the World, we are to expect and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:58560:83"/>be prepared againſt all Chances;</hi> but not diſmayed at the thoughts of any, ſeeing there is none of 'um that can be truly ſaid to be againſt us. And therefore <hi>Homer</hi> feign'd <hi>Aten</hi> the Goddeſs of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities to be bare Footed, as one that could not touch any thing ſharp or hard, but walk'd lightly over the heads of Men: Meaning that Adverſity dared not come near any but mean-ſpirited People. Wherefore lift up thine Eyes towards Heaven, where an everlaſting Reſt is prepared for thee.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Men in this world are like Trees,</hi> ſome ſlender, ſome great, ſome flouriſhing, ſome bearing Fruit, ſome withering, ſome growing, ſome blown down, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:58560:83"/>ſome fruitful, which in one Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt are brought together and laid upon one Stack. Neither is there afterwards any difference ſeen amongſt them, all being cut down, never more to grow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. So all Pride, Ambition, Riches, Authority, Children, Friends, and Glory, do in ſhort ſpace grow old, and Periſh: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will it ſignifie any thing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wert <hi>Irus,</hi> or <hi>Galba,</hi> or <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> or Noble <hi>Hercules.</hi> Only Vertue and Honeſty can make a Man happy: only a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſcience can make him mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. <hi>The worſt that good Men can fear, is the beſt that Evil can wiſh for, which is the deſtruction of the Soul in Death.</hi> But God has given us a ſufficient proof of our
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:58560:84"/>Immortality, by raiſing up his Son from the Dead. Were it not for this hope, our Lives would not be worth our care: So fluctuating and fooliſh a thing is Life. But our Creator has put us into this World in order to our tranſlation to a better; <hi>and ſecretly obſerves how we acquit</hi> our ſelves towards our Senſes, how we reſiſt the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of bad Examples, and what daily progreſs we make towards the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which is our native Country; <hi>for here we are but Pilgrims and Strangers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58560:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
